being here always a pleasure always a
pleasure
and uh just to let people know who's who
are listening uh
we've been having these q and a's every
two weeks but john's going back to a
school schedule
uh now and so we will be going
to a once a month schedule for these q
a's
they'll be held on the last monday of
the month but we've extended from one
hour to 90 minutes
so we have a little bit of extra time
and last time we took way too much time
with uh talking so let's get straight to
the questions we've got a question from
pedro
who who isn't able to be here today but
he
he left his question john what do you
think about
cell hypnosis and autogenic training to
help with focus
flow and to deal with the monkey mind
especially for triggering and intrusive
thoughts
do you have good sources for these
practices thanks
um so uh hypnotism is is
uh just to be clear all hypnotism is
ultimately self-hypnotism
um anybody who's hypnotizing is just
providing you with some external cues
and some mirroring and some
a redirection of attention so that you
actually hypnotize yourself
um and we also have to remember that all
people are not equally hypnotizable
so there's variation that way but
hypnotizability
seems to be heritable which means
there's
it's it's pl and matt rosano argues this
uh
it's plausible that it has been selected
for um
across human evolution i would argue
probably with matt rosano
uh back to the upper paleolithic
transitions it was probably enmeshed
with shamanic healing a capacity for
being healed by shamans
um again when i say that i don't mean
anything supernatural
um i mean uh you know the shaman is
doing ritual behavior
uh that can trigger uh self-hypnosis
that can magnify
the placebo effect and that's very very
powerful
in fact it's pretty much the only
significant health care you have
for the significant significant and
effective health care
you have for a very long time so i think
ignoring
uh hypno hypnotism uh in this overall
project would be a mistake
now for a long time there was that so
that was sort of that's an evolutionary
his
uh uh evolutionary psychology argument
uh some people still doubt its existence
i think that's no longer a plausible leg
to stand upon
people were saying uh individuals are
faking it
uh but then amir raz did a bunch of just
and he got you know canada research
chair just did a whole bunch of amazing
experimental work
uh showing that um you could hypnotize
people to overcome the stroop effect
and all kinds of other uh automatic
processing cognitive processing and
potential processing that people
can cannot override even with belief
etc etc so um everybody is now
basically flipped because of that very
seminal research
uh to come to the conclusion that hit
hypnotism is a real phenomena it's all
self-hypnotism
now uh amir uh raz and michael lischett
published a book uh on uh
hypnosis and meditation or hypnosis and
mindfulness oxford university press
um and uh myself and leo ferraro
um have a paper in there called
reformulating the mindfulness construct
and we picked up on some work
by amir raz and also by a colleague of
mine
uh uh norman farb norman farr pointed
out and
that most uh if you take a careful look
at the instructions people
are giving in mindfulness classes you
know
guiding people into a mindfulness state
and i do that
uh all the time many of you know that i
do the
weekday morning meditation contemplation
classes
roman farb pointed out that that um that
those instructions are
very similar very very similar
uh to hypnotic induction and so there
seems
what what leo and i argued is there
seems to be
a connection a causal interdependence
uh between uh hypnotism um the power of
suggestion
and uh mindfulness the power of
attention
and they can actually interford and
interpenetrate
each other and we we strongly suggested
building on that evolutionary argument
from matt rosano that i was just talking
about a couple of minutes ago
that in shamanic ritual you had these
two
things together um so that you have
something like um hypnotism
affording and strengthening people's
ability to get into mindfulness states
and then mindfulness um really
increasing people's ability
to enter into states of absorption and
flow that increase
their capacity for being hypnotized and
so
i do think they're so i i do think
there's a good scientific
basis now or trying to parse out and
then put
back together a relationship between
mindfulness um uh and hypnotizability
that's what we
argued uh in that paper in the in the
book
the chapter in that book so what that
means specifically
is i think we need i think the place i
would argue the place we need to look
for how to put those two together
um was is within um the effects of
ritual on cognition
paying attention for and perhaps
experimentally manipulating
mindfulness variables and hypno
hypnotism variables
so i think i mean i'd like to do that
and i'd like to do that moving forward
and then i'd like to
integrate that with work done by
nick wickelman and others about the use
of metaphor and an analogy
the language of coaching and how you
actually train people because it
it borders on both mindfulness and
hypnotism because you give these people
these inactive metaphors
you tell them you know uh you know run
up run sprint but sprint as if you're
running up a hill
or be a spring as you're moving around
and people sort of enact this and
um all these kinds of bizarre things
that we take is sort of natural
but nick's done a lot of work pulling
out um
that the role of sort of inactive
perspective and participatory
imagination
so i think all three of these need to be
studied um nobody's doing it
and then that leads me to my second
second part of my answer which
i can't recommend any good practical
work on this
uh precisely because i think that most
of the practical manuals
i haven't read them all and i i'm
largely ignorant but
so this is a
something of a mixture of a supposition
and conjecture
i think because this emerging science is
not available to
the was not available to the people who
have written all these books about
hypnotism
that these books are seriously
out of date and probably obsolete um so
i would hesitate to recommend any of
them
what i can predict is that much better
applications of hypnotism should be
coming down the pipe
as this further scientific work on the
relationships between hypnotism and
mindfulness which is already going
and then also i would propose the
relationships between hypnotism
mindfulness
and things like coaching imagination of
the
using imagination enacted imagination
and coaching
as that starts to unfold so it's a long
answer i think but
the point is that that that's a really
really interesting phenomena
and i have published on it because i do
think it's an important thing
uh to consider all right thank you
velasquin you had a question last time
that we didn't get to
yeah this don't i'm i'm sort of
wondering whether or not to ask it but
it's nice and quick so
i john i noticed the qualifications that
you've gotten to do the work that you're
doing
seems to be at least online is basically
a cognitive science bachelor's degree
and then
all the way up to phd in philosophy um
i was wondering if i wanted to get into
your work
would you recommend doing a load of
philosophy or can i just sort of do
cognitive science bachelor's
then maybe like a masters in philosophy
of mind
and then what like what's your advice
yeah yeah
yeah that's great uh so the yeah the way
it worked uh
it says because u of t doesn't have a
graduate cogside program
i actually did my phd basically in
cognitive science like that's
my thesis is actually entitled the
naturalistic imperative in cardinal
science
but i had to formally do it within uh
philosophy
so what my career went i got a ba and an
m.a
in sort of pure philosophy and i
realized
what i wanted to zero in on and i got
the uh honors
uh bsc in cognitive science and then i
went back and did my phd
uh basically in cognitive science i
would recommend just do straight
cognitive science
um you're gonna be doing a lot of
philosophy in that
and there are now graduate programs in
cognitive science that are quite good
andy clark's in edinburgh is very good
we have one in canada
at carleton university in ottawa i know
it'll be cold
uh well i guess it won't be it's
probably going to be online for a while
but those are two excellent places in
which you do
can do graduate work now that being said
i recommend and this is how the cog side
program is actually designed at the
university of toronto
so the it's designed so that you do a
double major you do cognitive science
and you major in another discipline one
of the home disciplines like psychology
or computer science
or philosophy or right uh or linguistics
so i recommend that all the way through
definitely in your undergrad do a double
major
outside like me philosophy that's the
thing you're most interested in
and then as you go through your graduate
degree make sure you do
a try and get as much of that double
doubling all the way along
research shows that if you have just
pure cog psi
you will be out competed by like if you
try to get
a job in a psych department or something
like that you'll be out competed by
somebody
who has a pure psych phd
but the same research shows that if you
have a cog
psi and psych degree you will
out-compete the person
that has just the psych degree um
especially if
the department is much more cognitively
oriented
um so i hope that's helpful feedback for
you
yeah thanks very much
great you have a question
hi john hey strong
how are you doing um
pretty good uh it's a little bit hectic
for me right now
um because i'm going in as brett
mentioned to teaching
the four courses which is more than a
full course load
um i'm now the director of the cognitive
science program at the university of
toronto
that's doing chewing up a lot of my my
time and energy
um so feeling a little spread thin but
other otherwise
lots of lots of good stuff happening had
a joyous time
uh talking with paul vander clay and
jonathan pagio
also had a really fun time talking with
uh jordan hall
and greg enriquez so so i'm also
i may be burning the candles at both
ends but there's at least some really
really shiny bits in that so yeah
i really enjoyed the conversation with
paul and uh jonathan archer if i've seen
the is this a recent one with um jordan
hall and greg
oh i haven't watched my channel yet
sorry that's been
jordan released that on his channel okay
so i'll check that out
anyway um did he get my email with my
question because i just realized it's a
bit of a mouthful
sorry i did and i i i did a quick read
of it
but it so you want to talk to me about
pan psychism
uh and contrast continuity and proposing
something sort of
um alternative uh to what jp marceau has
proposed so
please yeah okay um
so i was gonna read it out i've been
very interested in your conversations
with jp morso regarding pan psychos and
versus deep continuity
recently you mentioned that strong
emergence is something that many people
find hard to credit and i would have to
count myself
as being among that group however you
did say that psychism had similar
weaknesses with respect to the interplay
of mind and matter
and that this makes it hard to judge
which of the two theories are superior
so given that i also fall into the pan
cyclist camp
i would like to propose something to you
and i would like to invite you to take
your best shot at undermining it
you said that the weakness that pan
sorry
i was just laughing strong
okay you said that the weakness that pan
cyclism has
is that it isn't clear why in an
inanimate object such as rocks don't
have conscious experience
or basically if matter is supposed to
possess some form of consciousness
it isn't obvious how these rudimentary
consciousnesses are supposed to combine
to give us self-awareness
does my summary more or less get the
gist of your position yeah i just want
to emphasize that last point because
um it seems to me that pan psychism
like you and i think you're being an
accurate representative
they they criticize uh deep continuity
because
they reject strong emergence it seems to
me that they invoke some version of
strong emergence
and they say the you know something like
self-awareness and consciousness
strongly emerges
out of all the micro consciousnesses
that don't possess
intelligence and self-awareness and so
that's
for me that undermines why i would
choose pan psychism
over a deep continuity if both have to
rely on strong emergence
then the first pre uh seems to have a
much more conservative
ontology going for it and is much more
um
in concert with sort of existing uh
scientific ontology
so that's sort of the argument from i
think i said the same thing but i just
want to put a few points of emphasis on
it
yeah okay so that's great um i thought
you'd put it better than i could
and yeah i basically agree with
everything that you said there so
what i would like to propose is the idea
that space itself is the pan psych
which is to say that under this
hypothesis space locates
map to the body solid i think that we're
making this
movie it was strong so you say the last
two sentences again
you broke up for me i don't know if you
broke up for other people maybe your mic
was being moved or something like i
didn't get it i just didn't hear it what
did you just say the last two sentences
okay um so what i would like to propose
is the idea that space itself is the pan
psych which is to say that under this
hypothesis
space locates matter by being conscious
of it
are you with me so far okay
i think that this move uh removes
several of the weaknesses of the form of
pan cycles and the jp advocated
first of all while i can say that i i've
seen mata i can't say that i've ever
seen space
space is as much a conceptual
abstraction to me as your mind is
i have no reason to think that i have
direct experience of either
however scientific observation shows
that space and matter indeed interact in
some manner
specifically as einstein put it space
tells mata how to move and mata tells
space how to bend
but i would like to add to that
observation by stating that mata
potentially also fuses space in the form
of singularities
otherwise known as black holes if mata
can bend and fuse space
then could it not also perhaps break
space and could this breaking of space
not somehow form the basis of
consciousness as we know it
um i've got one more graph there i don't
know if you
if you want to cut in there or not okay
well um maybe i'll cut in here but i'll
try not to
uh sort of overwhelm you with a wave of
words
so do you get a chance to come to your
last paragraph
so i'm not so let's take
i mean this this was actually proposed
uh
and by all of all people was proposed by
newton
a leibniz clark debate in which clark
who was basically just a puppet for
newton
was debating leibniz and uh
newton actually proposed something like
that space was the censorium of god
and then people all jumped on him for
being a heretic
but so and the arguments are somewhat
similar
um
there seems to be an element of of
barclay's idea
too in there or maybe hume so when you
say you you can't
see space so
i mean a traditional response to that is
well
uh you don't see space you see motion
and that is to see space uh which
so you you see extension in things that
are not moving
and you see moving and move and you see
movement in things that aren't moving
and then right the the
category that makes sense of them
together is space
so are you saying
that that that set oh let me ask you a
question that i'll shut up
that second move of going from extension
in things
and being aware of motion and then
saying okay there's space because
of that that that's the that's a that's
a pure abstraction it's not something
that you directly experience
am i am i understanding you correctly
yeah it's something like like hume's
uh argument with respect to causality
that you you can't
ever experience causality right so in
other words you shouldn't expect
empirical proof for this
well i shouldn't necessarily expect to
have empirical proof
for your mind if it's if there's there's
a there's a barrier that
that cuts it off right but that doesn't
mean that you don't have a mind
right and so i mean sort of the response
right that's come you know post quine
and davidson
um right out of that is well
we the you know the problem with the
human standard of empirical evidence
is you end up having empirical evidence
for nothing you end up with human
skepticism
and then they point out that right in
science most empirical evidence
is for non-directly experiential things
right
right so but i'm saying so you can as
you make the move with space you make
the move with
mind and we don't know exactly what
space is we can only speculate using
mental abstractions and formulations we
can't ever
there's no at least today we don't know
of a test that allows us to
to directly um perceive the fabric of
space itself
it's a mystery to us
okay but but again that
that that same argument would work for
uh bacteria
right or or at least up till recently
when we had
you know microscopes uh because we could
only infer their existence but they
turned out to be real
right so well i mean i
i don't i expect you're not doubting the
reality of consciousness or space right
we but we know that or we we act as if
both of these phenomena are real
i i think i just misunderstood you i
think when you said there's no
i take empirical evidence to be anything
that provides
you know a basis for inferences to
theoretical entities
um because like i said okay yeah
i might be being a little bit more
strict than uh with my definition of
empire
yeah i do think it's like i think
there's empirical evidence for
you know for uh
you know dinosaurs living dinosaurs
i think there's empirical evidence for
space that's what i'm saying something
like that
um so uh yeah
well actually i think my last paragraph
will speak to this um
directly and then anyway so while i
understand
you said go ahead while i understand
that i've done nothing
to explain the mystery of the
interaction of matter and consciousness
i think that if we ever gain the means
to investigate the equally mysterious
relationship of space and matter
that the idea that i propose to you may
well become something that we can test
for in a falsifiable manner
and as a bonus i think this way of
dealing with con the consciousness
problem
would still be amenable to accounting
for the world in terms of tnm
information and the bridge of
intelligibility between them which is i
believe what you're using deep
continuity
to to actually do yeah
and so yeah i'm just going to steel man
your argument a bit i mean this
is increased uh by the
by the the move it's not rich consensus
but it's a powerful move within physics
for information realism to regard
information as a fundamental um
ontological building block along with
matter and energy space and time
and the reason you have to do this is
precisely because of paradoxes around
black holes
and other uh you know
other situations in which our sort of
our normal conceptions of space and time
are being warped uh to use star trek
language i suppose
um so that lends some initial
plausibility
uh to what you're saying uh i don't know
how else to respond to it
uh strong um
there it it like i said i i do think
that i mean you have some historical
precedent uh
platinus thought that everything is
contemplating even inanimate things
i mean he had a really interesting way
of understanding that
um i don't know yeah well i think i
could
i i could sorry i could jump in there
because
from your book cognitive science and
buddhism lectures when you were
describing the formal cause you used the
idea of the
form is kind of like shape but it
doesn't mean exactly shape and i think
while you were doing that because you
were trying to allude to the structural
functional organization but what i
wanted
what my response to you there is that i
think that there can be
there is an argument to be made that
space is exactly the formal cause and so
therefore the
space is shapeness itself right
yeah so yeah yeah and the fact that
if we both agree that space exists
then space is a real potential uh
in that way yes a real formal cause not
just a
conjectured possible thing well
i i would say a real possibility um
but i mean i prefer yeah i prefer to
talk of time in terms of potentiality so
but i don't know
that might just be a bit nitpicky and
besides the point for this conversation
i don't know
i don't i don't yeah i that's fine
that's fine i was i was using
potentiality because we were invoking
the aristotelian framework
okay fair enough fair enough okay well
yeah i think that's right
and i think and i mean i think there's
something deeply
um analogous uh between
um sort of the way things
i mean this is a white hedian argument
the way things
are constantly moving from
indiscriminacy to determinacy
and they are regulated by that kind of
formal causation and that's analogous
to something like relevance realization
and intelligence
and i've also argued there's important
continuity between intelligence and
consciousness
and if we throw in informational realism
i'm i'm trying to make your argument
more plausible in my own mind i hope you
you understand that um fair enough yeah
yeah but i mean i i i'm not convinced
but
i i think it's now a position i
well i've already i already take it
seriously i already take pansexism
seriously
uh but now even more so that's what i
can say at least at this moment
right um the one extra point that i
could put in there just to tie it in
with your stuff
is that i very much see space as a
perspective on matter so it's like
well mata there would be more
propositional to me yeah that's platynus
that's very much platinum of course
he doesn't have our notion of matter he
has that uh you know
on bodies he would say but very very
similar
very very analogous um is
what's the name of it is it that they're
on nature contemplation in the one
there's an
excellent book on that aeneid i'm trying
to remember the author
ah sorry anyways
uh the author wrote a book an extended
commentary on platinus's
aeneid nature contemplation of the one
in which she goes into that
that idea about everything is engaged in
an act of contemplation
you might find that very uh very useful
i've always found it something i keep
returning back to
uh like because i do think that's one of
platonus's more
profound energy so maybe take a look at
it and see if that gives you something
you could talk to me about
in the future oh yeah definitely
um yeah so and the only thing that i
left out there was with all this in mind
what's the most cunning philosophical
jiu-jitsu that you can
master against this idea but um we've
taken a lot of time i think i'll take
your steel manning instead
okay that's fine um you you you do
like i said i i don't see and you
admitted this upright so i'm not trying
to
pigeonhole you or jujitsu at all like i
said i don't think that resolves the
issue
uh that i had about the competition
between deep continuity and pan psychism
but
maybe it does well but i don't see that
right now
yeah i i would just say that i think
that it's
this if space is the pan in whatever uh
way mata breaks space it's not it's not
a strong emergence it's a weak emergence
in that case
and i think that's the advantage okay
but
well i like i think we should i think we
can go back and forth on this
okay uh so maybe we should leave it here
uh and i don't wanna i'll leave you i'll
leave you with the last word to be fair
to you
yeah well um i'll think it over some
more
and and get back to you and check out
the tightness and maybe you'll have
something more useful to say then
thanks john thank you
thanks you had a question last time that
we didn't get to
me um
yeah ben yeah go ahead then oh i see so
i i saw from the list that you haven't
text uh but that i
was next up there but i was hesitant to
assume because i didn't hear the name
um so uh well hi john
um just incidentally um
from that that last question you were
answering um with strawn
that book you mentioned that wouldn't
happen to be the one by uh a certain
john deck would it be
did i remember it correctly i i said
that and then i thought
and then i got a a memory error signal
coming up inside of me
yeah that would be it that's that's it
yeah okay well i can confirm that having
uh just looked at it okay thank you
thank you oh my memory was accurate
thank you
uh so the uh the question that i've been
hoping to ask you uh last week um
i have some awareness that maybe it's
it's malformed or misframed
but i'm pretty confident that you'll be
able to answer it in a way that's
productive
um what i was wondering is uh from your
perspective
as a cognitive scientist and as an
educator if you have any general advice
to people uh about how to um
to appropriate and uh optimize their
their process of learning
um and what i have in mind here
especially is um
jordan hall's idea about um trying to
emulate
special forces in in the sense of uh
getting that ongoing adaptability
yeah i think that's very very important
um
like jordan said so thank you for
bringing that that out
um
so um i'm actually trying
to finish up it's mostly written and
done
book on plausibility understanding and
pedagogy
called plausibility and pedagogy um
and so from the teacher's side i've been
trying to argue for shifting the
emphasis
from knowledge to understanding
because trying to get people to be
retainers of knowledge
um i'm not saying we should stop doing
that but trying to make that the primary
thing we do in education
is bloody obsolete and covet has made
that even more relevant
right um and and the universities i see
them struggling to try and catch up
uh because when a lot of the evaluation
is still from the paper
paper and pencil era in which you see
how much
information people have stored in their
otherwise fallible memory
and once we get into cova that becomes
completely irrelevant because of course
on those kinds of tests people can just
massively cheat and academic
dishonesty is skyrocketing right now
around that
so a lot of people are just struggling
um
and so um i guess sorry i i'm thinking
i'm sorry should calm down my
my tone is taking on i'm taking on the
tone of vindication
which is a little bit hubristic but i do
think an emphasis
on understanding and and i think this
goes along with what jordan is saying
is much more crucial and then that has
to do
with two things i talked about at length
but i talk about even more at length in
the book
i talked about them in the video series
awakening from the meaning crisis
which is plausibility and relevance
realization
and enhancing that um
and figuring and then
um doing it in a way in which you
enhance the cycle uh
that's found within deep learning within
neural networks you want to
you want to get a convergence that
compresses
um to some kind of construct
upon which you have optimal grip then
elegantly projects
into and transfers to many different
domains and introduces variation
that then feeds back in and you get deep
learning and that that kind of
balance between deep convergence deep
elegance
um implausibility i argue is how you
basically turn knowledge into
understanding
uh by train by tracing out ways in which
different pieces of information
different pieces of knowledge are
relevant to each other and convergence
relevant to each other in elegance and
relevant to each other
in in the higher order balancing between
convergence and elegance
so and i have actually been explicitly
teaching that way um and
and what that involves very much
is the
the the convergence saw it's two
different aspects of sort of socratic
method the convergence side
is uh the the method of
um considering many possibilities
intensifying the problem
until you get a convergence uh to a good
problem formulation
and then you use that to then trigger
convergence towards a proposed answer
from which you then want something like
a socratic insight
for how it's virtuous how it can be
applied in many different contexts
that's the method i've actually been
using um
and in the teaching of my courses
and i justify it again in terms of the
notion that
plausibility is the normative standard
we should be using
uncertainty is not a relevant standard
anymore
and in any ways any of our claims to
certainty
we suppose plausibility let me give you
a quick
example of what i mean like empirical
investigation
okay so i i can't uh consider
um all uh possible hypotheses
i i spilt it for the plausible ones and
then when i'm designing my experiment
i can't control for all possible
confounds i filter for the plausible
ones
and then once i get my results i can't
derive all of the implications
so i filter for the plausible one so
plausibility is presupposed before
during and after
any empirical investigation so if we
understand plausibility and
understanding
if we promote and emphasize training
people
more explicitly uh to
generate plausibility and thereby create
deeper understanding profounder
understanding
i think that is actually the tool that
is going to make
their they've learned
relevant to how things are changing
right now it's
so giving people a way to increase their
capacity for
understanding and filtering information
in terms of plausibility
i think that's most important and
relevant right now
so that
demands that we emphasize a whole bunch
of different sets of skills
than we have typically emphasized in
education
um so capacities uh for
abduction uh capacities for insight
capacities for reframing
capacities for wonder as opposed to just
curiosity
um so in order to open up um
your framing uh to significant
sub-correction
all of these things then uh take a more
central role
in pedagogy um did that
answer your question at all ben i said a
lot i don't know
well uh do you mind if i follow up just
a bit please
please well so i'm noticing the uh the
affinities with
zack stein and uh and james carson's
work of of course and uh
when you're ending on there um so it's
it's a bit like um what you laid out
there is part of the design criteria for
um sort of innovating pedagogy to
equip people um with the normativity of
plausibility
is that so
um but i'm also wondering
um and this is sort of another front
maybe or another um
angle of the question is um
how can people go about figuring out
what is
relevant for them to learn um
if you if you know where i'm going with
that um just given the
sort of vastness of um of what's
available
[Music]
um
that's i mean and what you're of course
alluding to here is the relevance
problem the frame problem
right um there's so much out there you
don't know what's going to turn out to
be
relevant in the long term so now
i can't give you a deductive inductive
argument i can give you
at most an aspirational argument for
this
but i think that's all we've ever been
given and it's just that
now that things are happening so rapidly
this what i just said has now been
made much more explicit
i think i mean and so this is for me the
socratic
thing uh and you know and the stoics
basically made this argument
um cultivate
wisdom and virtue and i argued that
virtue is the beauty of wisdom each
virtue is a way of being wise in a
particular
context you know it's a way of
appropriately
seeing what's the most relevant
information in this context that needs
to be done
um organized ultimately around the
meaningful life and human flourishing
uh cultivate the virtues that reduce
self-deception
and enhance meaning in life and then
you know cultivate what surrounds that
and afford it
for you and then cultivate what
surrounds that and affords that for you
so i'm proposing sort of you know
expanding
concentric circles um and this is how
i've tried to
to do it and i i see a lot of people
doing that these people that i'm talking
to
um and i think i think where did i argue
this can't remember i think this is a
version of how we can
make a much better uh you know
campbell's notion of following your
bliss which
tends to be just massively
misinterpreted in sort of a hedonistic
or romantic fashion i think if you find
everybody
everybody i think that should
start with the perennial practices of
reducing self-deception
enhancing meaning in life and then
find those things that fit
their particular historical cultural
context environmental context
their own idiosyncratic psychodynamic
history
and their personality variables
so that they can build a surrounding set
of affording practices
and hobbies or vocations or professions
and then build upon those etc etc um
and
why i'm recommending that is first of
all on one hand it has
i think a higher uh one of the higher
chances of being
successful because these perennial
patterns are constitutive
of human well-being and therefore they
should always be inherently valuable
and secondly because
the skills that are attendant to it like
rationality
um and wonder um and aspiration
are precise rationally more broadly
construed right
as i've argued these are also the skills
that seem to be the most reliably
generalizable across changing contexts
and situations
then you know and then and then if you
take a look at you do the reverse you
take a look at people's lives who have
gone well or going well
they tend to have that sort of structure
um where they've got sort of reliable
skills and habits and virtues meaning in
life and reducing self-deception
and then they sort of build outward upon
those
um in that supporting uh fashion now of
course
that's that is not a deterministic thing
i just said people get lucky
people uh you know lots of people who
get lucky
uh lots of people who do what i just
said you know suffer ill fate
uh we are only human beings we're not
gods and the universe is indifferent to
our narrative projects
um mostly um so
i think how you zeroing on what's
relevant
is what's virtuous and meaningful
and then what supports that
and then what supports the support etc
that's how i would answer that
so it's it sounds like there's almost an
anagogic resonance between the
the supports of wisdom and virtue and
wisdom and virtue and
um pushing forward to the horizon and
coming back and cultivating yeah that's
right
that's right and that that would be i
mean i didn't make that argument that'd
be a third argument
of what i proposed and you you picked up
on it very well thank you
um is you know that has a high
possibility of getting you to sort of
experience the sacred uh through sort of
reciprocal opening
and anagargic resonance and aspirational
self-transcendence
and all of those seem to make uh lives
better
and make the people living them better
in ways that seem
thus contextually cross-historically uh
validated
so uh
so just just one last thing uh as far as
reading for getting a plausible
understanding of plausibility
um i'm supposing that would be uh elia
milgram's work
yeah i mean one of the i mean
sorry this is uh i think the book that's
coming out is going to be that i'm
running i think it's the better
what it does is it takes rescher's work
and milgram's work
and also the stuff from deep learning
and sort of puts it all together into
well a plausible argument
right a plausible integrated argument
but those are the people like milgram
and rusher
there's a new book out called plausible
reasoning um
but but um there hasn't
and then there's lots of good books on
the other side on understanding
uh anthologies uh rect has some books on
understanding there's
an anthology from i think 2013 on
scientific understanding there's some
very good anthologies out there
on the philosophy and psychology of
understanding it's mostly coming out of
the philosophy of science
but if you want sort of i mean sorry
again
but the the i what i've tried to do is
draw all that literature together into a
single
argument in a single i'm sort of just uh
looking for what to read in the meantime
i suppose yeah yeah
um if i if you
uh i mean if maybe we could work out a
way in which
um i could email you uh the draft as it
exists
on the understanding and then that also
has an extensive bibliography in it
right
that way you'd get both the draft and
the bibliography
i would need from you some kind of you
know
statement just an email or something
that you know
right you won't you can't you won't
share it or
et cetera it hasn't been published
i'd be happy to do that yeah
um well then uh i suppose i'll email you
about that then
or that would be really great let's make
that happen that'd be good
no no thank you very much for uh for
proposing that
like i said as long as in the email you
formally you know formally state
my conditions um then there we go
be great well uh thanks so much john and
uh as always i appreciate you taking the
time
and um that's something that i
and that i i i'm really putting a lot of
thought into right now
i i have so many things that are 90 done
uh and i'm trying to bring them to
fruition but
um i'm just incredibly busy right now so
um
the rate at which things are coming to
completion is is i think is being
slowed down a bit so that's why i've
gotta free up some space so i can
finish up these other things that which
will in turn free up more space
at least that's the fantasy i tell
myself right and there are new projects
coming in the meanwhile and
of course of course yeah
so i i suppose i'll pass the floor back
to bread
the last two people on our backup list
aren't here so
if you guys were holding off adding
yourself to the queue because you
thought we'd run out of time
and we have an extended uh time tonight
we're going uh until
another another 40 minutes or so uh you
know please add yourself to the list
valerie you are up next thank you very
much
uh thank you john i really appreciated
your
lecture series awakening from the
meeting prizes i learned a lot from it
and i also enjoyed your latest
discussion with uh
jonathan bishop and and paul vander clay
that was
very lively and informative i really
didn't understand
eminence and uh
from the bottom up from top down thing
um i had a more of a personal question
and you may not
feel comfortable answering this if not
please take an orange
but i was just kind of curious what got
you into
cognitive 5
so that's actually a
big i'm happy to answer it uh
it's it's it's just somewhat convoluted
thing um so um
i was brought up uh within a a very
fundamentalist
um christian upbringing and then in my
teens i basically
rejected that because i encountered uh
some
really some very uh profound and
thought-provoking world literature
sort of broke things open for me um but
that of course
um bought with it um
i guess uh my own um
extreme version of something like the
meaning crisis
i went looking around um
and i entered into university and i took
a philosophy course and i met
the figure of socrates in the work of
plato's and this had a profound
impact on me um and i i saw in that
something that i was hungry for this
topic of wisdom self-examination
life of aspiration and virtue
those topics really really moved me
profoundly
and i decided to take that out
but as in fact not that much further
in academic philosophy all of the you
know that whole socratic project of the
cultivation of wisdom and the topic of
wisdom
off the table you couldn't even take a
course when i was an undergrad on the
stoix or or
or the neoplatonus that's how that's how
truncated things were and
it was all it was all about knowledge
and epistemology and not about wisdom
and and the love of it and so that i got
very disillusioned that
um in one sense i i i came to really
value
um the meta science and um
the cultural critique that academic
philosophy was affording me
so i continued on and i got my ma but by
that time
i became very sort of disenchanted with
that project
and i actually left school for a year
and beca and i i fell into a pretty dark
state
and then i i sort of committed myself to
finding
um finding finding somewhere else where
i could start to cultivate wisdom and i
took up
tai chi chuan and uh
the past meditation and contemplation
and related practices
and i started to practice these very
deeply and they were ha
was just having a profound
transformation on me
and um and
you know i i there's overlap i'm
presenting it like it's a nice clean
sequence but
it's all it's muddied and overlapping
but i'm sort of i'm
cleaning it up for the purposes of
narrative um
and so i started to pursue that
and then i realized that there was a new
discipline that was starting to talk
about
mind body and mind really right and and
consciousness
at least in ways that uh i'm not
saying as you know this interest i was
having in wisdom was at least
closer to it than academic philosophy
that was cognitive science
so i decided to take it up and as i was
taking it up
i started to get more and more into it
but cognitive science was itself going
through a change
what was starting to happen is that
cognitive science and then
very close to it cognitive psychology
were starting to come around
where they were talking about
consciousness and altered states of
consciousness
and uh you know
rationality and then very soon wisdom uh
the book on wisdom came out in 1990 uh
edited by
robert sternberg so all of a sudden
all these topics that i was learning
about where i was cultivating wisdom
were now in cognitive science and
cognitive psychology so
those two just came together for me and
they started reinforcing each other
and then it just became
uh it went from something i was studying
to a vocation i had a sense of being
called to this
because of that convergence and the way
it seemed such of a kairos it seemed to
resonate with my students
and then seems to start and then that
sense of resonating with the culture at
large
uh started to grow on me um and so
that's how it happened
wow cool thank you very much i really
appreciate that
i uh one last thing i'd like to share
with you is the
i know you probably heard this a lot but
the agape
um uh section in your lecture
that really blew me away i've never
heard anyone articulate it so perfectly
before
and i really enjoyed your lecture series
and
the history was very fascinating i never
finished college so
it was it was probably the best uh
tallest course i could take online
to learn all of that from you so thank
you very much for your work and thank
you for sharing your story with us
well thank you for saying that um that
episode on agape i mean there's there's
several episodes in the
in the series that touched me very
personally
um but that episode touches me maybe one
of the deepest
which is and i i i care a lot about it
not just because i think agape is
important
so the the the the shareable reason the
reason i can share with other people is
i think agape
is tremendously important and i've made
lots of arguments about why that's the
case
but for me uh and i
and i don't want to be presumptuous uh
about
anybody's religious orientation or
affiliation i always try to be very
respectful of that
for me and i'm just speaking for me on
this point
um that was a way in which i was
it was a culmination of a long
process of trying to
reappreciate jesus of nazareth
as for me a sage figure um
and to make to
to recover from my religious
past something of the man
and his teaching and so that was for me
also a personally healing episode
wow well thank you for sharing that
that's
that's very insightful and it took
years for you to figure that out
so thank you for saying that and thank
you for your encouragement it's much
appreciated
you're welcome and thank you i'll turn
the baton over to whoever is
next
okay this may be a good segue to
talking you talked about how you started
your ecology of practices
john maybe you could just expand on
the importance of an ecology of practice
and talk about
what's going on now in the meditation
course which is
expanded beyond meditation to to the
wisdom of hypatia
and uh maybe maybe tell us a bit about
what's going on there and the importance
of it
thank you thank you for the opportunity
to do so i appreciate that
um so yeah i mean i was as i mentioned
to valerie i was taught in ecology
practice
and it took me quite a while to
retrospectively understand
uh the pedagogical profundity of that um
and
how it afforded the transformation and
then the cognitive science i was
learning about cognitive complexity
cognitive complexification and
exactation
and cognitive flexibility just all
converge with that
um so the idea of an ecology of
practices is that any psychotechnology
um has you know strength and weaknesses
and what you want to do each
psychotechnology
is in some sense um affording you some
capacity for self-correction
like mindfulness self-correction of
attention for example
um but but that can be undermined by the
fact that
that psychotechnology uh can to
some degree also be a source of bias
misdirection etc um and so you want uh
uh psychotechnological practices uh to
be put into opponent processing
um so at a higher you're getting a
higher order
a more comprehensive form of
self-correction so
one of the ones they offer for example
is you know
mindfulness practices um
tend to afford insight and they tend to
reduce your inferential processing
um
they tend to increase the insight
machinery and that's
that's a very good thing the problem
with the insight machinery is that's
also the same machinery
by which you jump to conclusions and
you you give in more quickly to your
intuitions and so that
that needs to be counter balanced with
things like active open-mindedness
which tend to dampen down that machinery
and
increase and foreground the inferential
the problem with pure active
open-mindedness is it
is it doesn't it can get you into a
rigidity a locking in of your framing
uh an inability to afford insight and so
they have respective strengths and
weaknesses and you need to have them
together within mindfulness you need
meditative practices
uh that are designed to get you to step
back and reflect on the patterns and
processes of your mind
and they need to be counterbalanced with
contemplative practices
that get you to look through that
reframing and see if you can realize
deeper patterns
um in the world so what you have is you
have that and it's
like an ecology you have these nested
relationships at different scales
in which things need to be put into
opponent processing
so they counter balance and mutually
afford
and constrain each other so
at a very high level what we're doing in
the sangha so within
the thing and we were already pursuing
pursuing that uh that sengo is what i
refer to
that's the community that has built up
around morning meditation class
so i taught people uh you know the past
meditation and then i taught them a
contemplative practice
uh which is uh uh meta
and then i taught them how to put them
together into a kind of opponent
processing
that actually um exacts into a higher
state uh prajna
uh but i also taught them how to balance
all these
sitted non-moving forms of mindfulness
with moving practices
and so you can see that what's happening
is the complexification of multi-scaled
um opponent processing and ecology but
all of those things are really centered
on various aspects of mindfulness and if
you remember what i said earlier
the problem with all of these
mindfulness practices
is uh they need to be counterbalanced
uh by other kinds of practices um
like aom and active open mindedness is
basically drawn from
stoicism and stoicism is one
of the wisdom traditions uh within
the west we're making use of a book
right now
so we have these eastern these these
practices
an ecology of practices drawn from the
eastern traditions
you know drawn from buddhism vipassana
meta
drawn from taoism tai chi chi kung uh
uh each one janjung and now
we're now going through the western uh
wisdom traditions
um all of so if right
you know the buddha is sort of a an
exemplary figure for the eastern
traditions
socrates is the exemplary figure from
the western traditions
and we're actually going through you
know uh in
uh we're going through mcclellan's book
the wisdom of hypatia which is basically
a course
where primary school is uh epicureanism
and the epicurean practices
and then you graduate from that into
high school where you learn the stoicism
and the stoic practices that i mentioned
earlier and then you graduate from that
into the neoplatonic practices
and so you get the right so that's sort
of you go primary school to high school
to
sort of university level then
and and each one's for each one built it
compensates and corrects and builds and
deepens it complexifies
and so what you end up with is a rich
ecology of practices drawn from the
western tradition
and i i i agree with uh arthur versus
lewis that neoplatonism
is the sort of cultural cognitive
historical grammar of western
spirituality
neoplatonism is how you get you know it
it's how you get
christian mysticism that's how you get
uh islamic mysticism
and sufism um it's how you get things
like kabbalah and judaism
etc um and and um
of course it was first for a long time
uh either publicly or under persecution
um
in hiding it was also just itself an
independent spiritual tradition
um and so uh the idea is
to give people that huge
uh western stream ecology of practices
and then at the very a very high level
you have this opponent processing
uh between the eastern and western
orientations
and so you get a very high level um
uh capacity for self-correction
for aspiration at the same time you get
a rich reservoir of practices
that allow for a very significant
pluralism
while also giving people shared
processes shared language uh shared way
of communicating and communing together
and i think this is perhaps very helpful
for a pluralistic world going through uh
rapid uh historical socioeconomic and
cultural change
brett was that okay did that sort of do
it yeah
yeah that's great and and for for
anybody who's listening now who hasn't
been following along
on youtube for the last number of months
is it too late for them to
to start getting into your course no no
no no i don't think so
um so one of the things that amar my
good friend
and my technical advisor and then also
my son jason
what we've been doing is we have we have
recorded all of the lessons
um um so you all in fact we've recorded
every single session
we've recorded all the lessons and what
you can do
is you can go in and like do the lessons
you know do one or two
maybe even three lessons a week um
probably two's best
um and you know and then work your way
through but it
but then um as you're doing that you
could meet in and
start you know where we are in the
wisdom of hypatia
there's lots of resources by which
people and lots of people have done this
uh we try to pace things up they've been
able to they've started at all different
times
and been able to catch up and integrate
in
so i don't think that would preclude
people at all
and we've been meeting at 9 30 in the
morning along with you here in the
discord uh many of us
uh to to to do your your course with you
to meditate and to talk about it
and of course you're we're starting to
to add well we're going to be adding
very soon
a new exercise that's going to take
place on the discord
or coordinated through the discord uh on
in terms of
what do you call a philosophical
fellowship yeah it's philosophical
contemplative companionship
it's sort of the one of the core
practices core
group practices um that i think is
inspired by epicureanism uh uh
it would lead to belong to what i would
call extended epicureanism yes
and so can you just talk really briefly
about
what what that we will be dividing into
groups and then what what we'd be doing
together
um so what yeah um
one thing is to recommend people check
out um
meditating with john verveinke the class
i gave on friday
the class i gave today um if they wanted
to get a quick
a little bit more sorry a little less
quick a little bit longer
like more extensive presentation but the
basic idea is
um learning a way
of reading and speaking
sorry that's the wrong word to erase
what i just said
i was trying to i was building a
contrast in my mind and then i blurted
out the wrong thing
very often we we think about things and
we speak about them and we speak
to people and and and that's very useful
for all kinds of reasons
what you wanted to learn to do is
instead
not to about a text but learn how to
think through it
uh uh you know some short philosophical
text
as a way of picking up the way that
person
thought like how plato thought or how
spinoza thought
because a good way of thinking about
this is most
of our deepest aspirational learning and
transformation comes from role modeling
i mean you probably heard this uh i
heard it a lot growing up as a kid
you know kids pay a lot more attention
to what you do than what you say
uh because they imitate you they try and
take they try to see things the way you
see them
and they try and that's how they work
whereas they pay
precious little especially in the teen
years to what you say
so the child is to the adult the adult
is to the sage you want to
read a text together you want to try and
presence
that person like plato's perspective or
spinoza perspective
not because you agree with it but also
don't disagree with it
don't think at it and don't speak to
people try to
to collectively give voice to it uh so
that you can more and more
start to sense what it would be like
to see the world in a platonic fashion
all around
right and see yourself and others in
that in a platonic fashion
or a spinozistic fashion or a stoic
fashion
um or you know a buddhist fashion
and and so the idea there is is to
collectively uh come into a
contemplative place where you're looking
through the text
and you're looking through what you say
together through in both meanings of the
word
uh by means of and beyond
so that who can role model in a profound
way sage's
way of seeing and being and that's
that's to cultivate a kind of
companionship together
a fellowship around practice
that has us coming into
consonance and coherence with these
powerful visions of the depths
of what human beings can be
in the depths of how the world can be
disclosed to them
so that's the the the the nature of the
practice
now there's a bunch of i mean that
sounds very abstract
but there's actually some there's very
specific uh procedures and sequences of
procedures that i've taught that people
can use to actually do what i'm talking
about
and i see this as a seed practice one of
the things you do in oncology practice
is you layer them
i've had a lot of feedback recently uh i
got some excellent feedback from nick
winkelmann
um on this very point um really
brilliant guy his language of coaching
really important book
um and he said you know
he said to me you know you i realize
that you have all these things and then
they layer and converge together
and that happens over time and so what i
mean
by an ecology of practices is it should
also layer
uh so i think uh this is
that philosophical contemplative
companionships
train and are seed practices uh
for a neoplatonic practice down the road
of dialectic which i hope to also
um uh i i guess you as you probably know
brett i'm doing a lot of work on that
with a lot of people to try and
sort of uh reinvent you that so uh i
think
all of these are important because we
have lost
have lost dialectic and which is
a process of opponent processing and
self-correcting
we have lost it in debate which has
become
almost completely zero sum and
adversarial and
we are we we have lost communing
together that's what i'm describing and
we have reduced it merely to
communication
which we have then reduced to simply
sending signal
and trying to make sure that our signal
uh gets to where we want it to go to do
what we want it to do
and that is um not
conducive to wisdom and it's not
conducive
to giving people the kinds of
experiences
that open them up to overcoming
self-deception
and to enhancing the connectedness to
themselves to each other into world
that is generative of increased meaning
in life
so that that's why there are there's so
much hunger
for these forms of dialogue and
discourse
that are centered on communing
the logos as opposed to just
communicating within debate
so that's what i would say about that so
much and hopefully
uh some of you guys listening will want
to join us as well
so mark you have a question
yeah sorry about that um
hey john um i'm going to return your
favor
from uh the last time we talked and sort
of ask you what what
actually is maybe a bit unfair and is
sort of an
indecent question in some sense
for which i'll i'll apologize in advance
and
feel free to skip any of the difficult
parts of this sort of
uh three-part thing that i'm i think i
can outline
so i'm having a uh
i'm literally struggling over the topic
of addiction and
um i'm wondering
sort of in three aspects like i see sort
of two definitions of addiction right
the
anything that you're doing that's
getting in the way of other things that
you should be doing
right and then i sort of realized rather
recently actually that that's
a poor model some people are sort of
slaves to their addiction even though
it's not
or not apparently getting in the way of
anything and then
right there's self-deception so you
can't use the first definition because
if there's self-deception you won't
you won't even notice uh that you that
you have that
addiction and that and then i you know
it seems to me
like that fits into the meaning crisis
in some important way that that
that i'm not i'm not sort of
understanding
and and you know i don't know what your
thoughts are around that so that that
that i think you can you know address
easily
clarification when you said that do you
mean that
poor definition of addiction
addiction itself is it okay so i didn't
know which this was sorry
yeah yeah it's because i'm my thoughts
are unclear on this and this is a
difficult topic for me for whatever
reason
so yeah how does addiction fit into the
meaning crisis which is what i wrote
down i don't know why i can't read today
uh and then and then you know you're
more on the you know more to the point
and maybe you shouldn't even touch this
and and so
you know again i apologize what other
practices like how do we
help release ourselves from addiction
like what what are the things that we
can do to even
practices that we can engage in that
maybe we find addictions that we didn't
know
existed in some sense so that those are
the sort of the three layers that i that
i want to
you know and feel free to riff on the
definitions too because
like i i have never given this enough
care
right and so i'm sort of coming out this
new in in some sense which is strange to
me but
yeah anything you could go on on riff on
that topic would be great
thank you that's great mark um so first
of all an important caveat
this is something this is a part of my
thinking
that is still i'm still a work in
progress um
and maybe i don't mean that in the sorry
everything i'm doing is still a work in
progress what i mean by that is
i'm not too i'm not at a place where i'm
completely satisfied
uh you know presenting it um
in any kind of uh recommended manner uh
so i
but i i want to hmm but i'm going to i'm
going to
let's do so given that caveat and given
that what i i'm saying is not meant to
uh be anything other than
preliminary why do i why do i say that
because as i
as i did explicitly arguing i'm
confident about this first point the
model of addiction
in our culture is going through a major
transformation
and you're correct mark um so we had an
old model which was uh the disease model
and then the criteria for establishing
that were exactly
uh the ones that you gave uh which is
you know uh well how do we know when
someone is diseased well
they're they they are incapable of
functioning normally
and they therefore need our help uh so
um
right and and of course the degree of
loss of functionality
like a cold we we maybe allow people a
day off
uh but some diseases uh you know like
hiv
requires significant intervention um and
therefore you can put addictions on
something analogous the disease scale
and then you measure them by how
dysfunctional people's lives get
and and then what we'll do is we'll call
it when people's lives are dis
functional in three domains um you know
work um and relationship and basic
health
self-care um that's when a person's
addicted
so and and that hap okay
so that diagnostic right those
diagnostic criteria
they have they had value they they did
help uh to
zero in on people that needed help um
but they were based on a model the
disease model
that has been increasingly undermined
uh by a lot of empirical evidence
um and by a lot of good theoretical
argumentation
and uh you know that's where and at the
for and i've seen many people are doing
this
the person that who's taught me the most
on this um
and who's at the forefront of this is
mark lewis and his notion
uh that addiction is a learned behavior
it's reciprocal narrowing
and as i've mentioned before i i the
idea i got of
understanding anagage as reciprocal
opening and the opposite
of addiction um came up in
a dialogue i was having with mark lewis
then that leads me to a point
that that you i think we're bringing up
which is
addictions if we see addiction as
right moving in the direction
predominantly because we're talking
probabilistically we're talking
dispositionally we're not talking about
every moment of your life
if we say that people are predominantly
moving in reciprocal narrowing
uh that should be thought of is in some
way addictive
and the cap if they're moving uh away
from that reciprocal opening
um that that's that's that is in some
way
the ultimate therapeutic kind of
response
but we should then broaden the notion of
addiction
uh much more comprehensively and this
this goes into what you talked about uh
let me give you an example what i'm
talking about
i think uh you know eric fromm's modal
confusion in which people get
locked into um a vicious cycle of
reciprocal narrowing because they get
locked into the having mode
they lose access to the being mode they
can function and this is part of fraum's
argument tonight this is i'm going to
steal man your point
they can function in in our society
and you know and promise point is that's
because our society is
is in some major ways insane and that
society is actually driving that
modal confusion and so although they are
locked into reciprocal narrowing
they aren't meeting the sort of standard
criteria
given by the society of being functional
they're probably
successful in their right in in their
in their in their careers and their you
know the fact that they've had
several marriages maybe that's a form of
success it means that
they sort of are constantly trading up
and all the kinds of framing critiques
so the point is when you use the
standard criteria based on the
really inadequate model of addiction you
have
too narrow a scope of which you're
looking for addiction
and i was going to say this when you
when you mentioned
um that that the the sort of normal
criteria even when people were using
that criteria
those criteria they knew it was
inadequate because
people can right that people can be
functional to a very
significant degree and right still have
all all kinds of other markers at least
standard markers of addiction but
they're they're they're in a highly
dysfunctional situation
they may have all kinds of people
co-opted around them enabling them
and therefore they don't lose their
career their health doesn't suffer
their relationships are managed by other
people and so
um the the individualistic nature
of that criteria is also misrepresenting
so when we talk about addiction and we
move to this kind of more comprehensive
model
we have to look at how
self-deception can be masked not only
by internal mechanisms like bias
and parasitic processing but also by
external conditions
cultural cognitive grammars um
socioeconomic
uh institutions and structures um
that can prevent people from getting out
of
uh the kinds of reciprocal narrowing
that nevertheless is dysfunctional in
way like
notice how peop many people who would be
satisfying standard
uh criteria for not being addicted but
but
their reciprocal narrowing is starving
them into a kind of
zombie version of the meaning crisis and
they're totally unaware of it but
but you know there's there they lack
meaning in life
and therefore they have a tremendous
brittleness at the level of mental
health um in terms of moral aspiration
etc
so i think that
we need to more deeply
uh think about
addiction in terms of reciprocal
narrowing
we need to make central self-deception
and how self-deception
bleeds out into things that were not
considered
medically forms of addiction and that
that has to do not only with internal
processes
but internal external environments the
agent arena relationship
of course is paramount in my mind and
what that means to me
is that i think
obviously people should sorry i want to
i want to make this really clear
people i mean people still should be
pursuing
um you know therapeutic interventions
both individual
and group therapies uh they should
and they should pursue therapies that
are increasingly more
embodied than just sort of standard cbt
and things like that
um but i think we have we're coming to
the realization
this is where again i feel most
incomplete in what i'm saying in most
tenuous but we're coming to the
realization that a lot of
uh addictions not the way i've now
more broadly construed them and
portrayed them um
they require a sacred response
and you say that's crazy well is it uh
we know that something that looks a lot
like sacredness
uh which is you know a mixture of
uh you know some a psychedelic to
enhance cognitive flexibility
and then a ritual narrative uh
situation like therapy that combination
is way more powerful
dealing with depression and the thing
about depression is it doesn't fall
under our standard definitions
of addiction but man does it ever fall
under uh reciprocal narrowing and
parasitic processing
and having environmental factors as well
as internal factors
and so opening up the idea
that we need a sacred dimension
in the response to a lot of addiction
i think is important now many of you are
saying and and this is a good point
i'm acknowledging it well that sort of
spiritual dimension has always been
present you know you know with
alcoholics anonymous
or you know there's a buddhist version
uh for alcoholics anonymous that makes
use of the eightfold path rather than
a christian framework it's actually by
the way um empirically seems to be more
successful than a.a
um i don't know what that says it
doesn't say that buddhism is more true
than christianity
or anything ridiculous about that it
points to the point i'm trying to make
is
yeah but we we we could get better at
understanding
the the sacredness and we could do
better at implementing it and
integrating it and using it
in how we respond to individual
addiction but we also would then turn it
outward
and need to in a coordinated fashion use
it to respond
to collective cultural addictions
so um that's nowhere near enough mark
it's it's
like it's it's inadequate in a lot of
ways there's lots of lacuna what i said
but that's where my thinking is at right
now about that
wow that was yeah that was as always
john
that was fantastic that was a lot more
uh comprehensive
uh we'll say than i thought and then
just quickly
is there anything you think in terms of
practices i mean i didn't know this
about the eightfold path and the
aaa you know because a i always thought
was the best but
um is there anything in terms of
practices to sort of
overcome the self-deception about say
whether or not we're depressed
because to your point yeah it's an it
looks like an addiction
or or and then and then treatment is
there you know other than just like
sacredness is there something
you can point to specifically maybe
maybe as part of the
like the meditation ecology practices
series that you're that you're teaching
or
i do think i do think um i do think
um a richly layered ecology of practice
um that is oriented both internally and
externally like we're trying to do in
the sangha
um has the highest plausibility
uh and probability uh plausibility in
the sense in terms of its
intelligibility and justification
and probability in terms of prediction
of its success uh
for doing what you said getting people
to realize
in fact um so i don't
again i don't have scientific evidence
but i have
too close to two decades
of anecdotal evidence that this is often
what happens when people enter these
wisdom
pathways they come in for one reason
people here let me like an extended
example i want to meditate because i
want to relax and get rid of stress
and as they do this they start to see
forms of self-deception that they were
not aware of
that were are sort of underlying and
causing but deeper than
the stress factors and then they start
to wake up to that and they do that
because of the practices but you know
the buddha the dharma that's saying it
they do it because of the practices
uh they do it because they get a new
cultural cognitive grammar
by which they can articulate and reflect
and they get it because of a sangha they
get it because of
you know groups of people through which
they can self-transcend and self-correct
so i think yeah that has um the greatest
uh plausibility and probability of
helping people awaken to forms of
self-deception
that are so self-masking that people
aren't not even initially aware of them
that's great thanks john i i appreciate
it i i apologize to the difficult
question but as usual you handled it
excellently
thank you well thank you mark for saying
that and thank you for your
charitability i appreciate that
really close to the end of our time uh i
think raleigh do you have a comment
yeah hi john actually actually i i would
like to use this chat a chance to
to say thank you very very much uh
actually uh first of all i'm so lucky
for knowing you i actually have no
question
but i wanna there's a lot of things to
thank you for so i'm not gonna count
them all but the two things stand
uh out them the first of them is thank
you very much for prof
uh providing a platform in the sangha
where
where there is a feeling of relatedness
and and looking forward into the future
uh for love for wisdom and
second thing is that as a student of
cognitive neuroscience
i want to thank you for being an ideal
in my life which is something i'm
missing so much in academia today in my
life so thank you very much for that
thank you for saying that all um
um that's that that's very that's that
uh
touches me deeply um both
in different ways um
it's very encouraging to me it's very
encouraging to me
so thank you thank you making me
it's from a heart from from the depths
to the depths from emergence to
emergence as you said then
thank you i like that thank you very
so much john again that was another
great uh session
uh to remind everybody uh so so we're
changing our schedule a little bit
uh because john's getting back to the
grind
of uh of the fall semester
and so we're going to be doing these uh
these q and a's
on the last monday of the month uh we're
gonna have a little bit of a time change
they're gonna move from
six until 6 30 eastern but they're going
to go for 90 minutes so
so the last monday of the month month
from 6 30 till 8
is how we're going to be moving forward
and again thanks john and thanks
everyone for being here today
thank you everyone thank you so much
thanks john thank you thanks thanks
all right awesome thanks john yeah
thanks john and brett appreciate it
thanks for doing this
thanks so much everyone take good care
have a good evening